<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alebarberis.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://alebarberis.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-21T19:01:03+00:00</updated><id>https://alebarberis.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">personal website on github</title><link href="https://alebarberis.github.io/blog/2023/github-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="personal website on github"/><published>2023-03-06T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-06T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alebarberis.github.io/blog/2023/github-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alebarberis.github.io/blog/2023/github-website/"><![CDATA[<p>Are you ready to create your own personal website but are feeling overwhelmed by the process? Don’t worry, you’re not alone! I’ve been in the same boat, wanting to build my own website for ages, but always putting it off because I thought the process of creating something I truly loved would be too time-consuming.</p> <p>But recently, I stumbled upon some academic webpages hosted on GitHub that caught my eye. To my surprise, I learned that many of these websites were built using templates as a starting point, making the process of building a website much simpler than I had previously thought.</p> <p>Feeling inspired, I decided to take the plunge and create my own site. And guess what? I found the process to be quite straightforward and pretty enjoyable! So if you’re interested in creating your own website but aren’t sure where to start, keep reading. In this blog post, I’ll share the different steps I followed to get my website up and running. Who knows? Maybe it will inspire you to do the same!</p> <h2 id="my-setup">My setup</h2> <p>I used a MacBook Pro laptop running macOS 13.1 for this project. However, the steps described in this post should also work on other operating systems, as <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> is designed to be platform-agnostic. Keep in mind that some commands and tools may have different syntax or require different installation procedures depending on your system, so you may need to adapt the instructions accordingly.</p> <h2 id="0-prerequisites">0 Prerequisites</h2> <p>Before you start building your website, it’s important to ensure that you have a <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> account. If you don’t have one, you can create a new account and log in to get started. Additionally, we will need support from <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>, a static site generator that’s great for creating blogs and personal websites.</p> <p>To make sure that Jekyll is properly installed in your system, you can run:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">jekyll <span class="nt">-v</span></code></pre></figure> <p>If missing, read the next section and follow the instructions for installation (or see visit <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> site).</p> <p>With these two tools, you’ll be well-equipped to start building your website!</p> <h3 id="install-jekyll">Install Jekyll</h3> <p><a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> is a static site generator that takes text written in a markup language and uses layouts to create a static website. To use it, you’ll need to ensure that your system has a few dependencies installed:</p> <ul> <li>Ruby version 2.5.0 or higher</li> <li>RubyGems</li> <li>GCC and Make</li> </ul> <p>To check if Ruby and RubyGems are already installed on your system, you can run two simple commands:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">ruby <span class="nt">-v</span>
gem <span class="nt">-v</span></code></pre></figure> <p>If you receive output that indicates the versions of Ruby and RubyGems, you’re good to go! We can install jekyll by running:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">gem <span class="nb">install </span>jekyll bundler</code></pre></figure> <p>If not, you’ll need to install them (see section below) before you can use <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>.</p> <h3 id="install-ruby">Install Ruby</h3> <p><a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> is a popular open-source programming language known for its dynamic and flexible nature. If you’re interested in using Ruby, you’ll need to install it on your system. Fortunately, there are several tools available to simplify the installation process, such as <a href="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</a> and <a href="https://github.com/postmodern/chruby">chruby</a>.</p> <p>If you’re a macOS user, it’s worth noting that while Ruby comes preinstalled on your machine, it’s recommended to install a separate and newer version using a version manager like <a href="https://github.com/postmodern/chruby">chruby</a> or <a href="https://rvm.io/">rvm</a>. This will ensure that you have access to the latest features and security updates. For my own installation process, I followed the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/macos/">Jekyll</a> guide and used <a href="https://github.com/postmodern/chruby">chruby</a>.</p> <p>To check if <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> is already installed on your system, you can run the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ruby -v</code> command in your terminal. If you see a version number displayed, you’re good to go. Otherwise, you’ll need to install <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> before you can proceed with using it.</p> <h4 id="install-homebrew">Install Homebrew</h4> <p>The first step to installing Ruby on your macOS or Linux system is to install <a href="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</a>, a package manager that makes it easy to install software that isn’t included with your operating system. <a href="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</a> allows you to easily install, upgrade, and manage packages and dependencies on your system. To install Homebrew, you can run this simple command:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">/bin/bash <span class="nt">-c</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">$(</span>curl <span class="nt">-fsSL</span> https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh<span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">"</span></code></pre></figure> <h4 id="install-chruby-and-ruby-install">Install chruby and ruby-install</h4> <p>To install <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">chruby</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ruby-install</code>, we can simply run the following command in our terminal:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">brew <span class="nb">install </span>chruby ruby-install xz</code></pre></figure> <h4 id="install-ruby-1">Install Ruby</h4> <p>Once installed, we can use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ruby-install</code> to download and install the specific version of <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> that we need.</p> <p>For example, to install the latest stable version of <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> supported by Jekyll, we can run:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">ruby-install ruby 3.1.3</code></pre></figure> <p>This will take few minutes.</p> <h4 id="configuration">Configuration</h4> <p>After installation, we can switch to the newly installed Ruby version using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">chruby</code>. However, before doing that, you’ll need to configure your shell to automatically use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">chruby</code>. This is typically done by adding a few lines of code to your shell configuration file, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.bashrc</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.zshrc</code>. For example, I ran these commands:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"source </span><span class="si">$(</span>brew <span class="nt">--prefix</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">/opt/chruby/share/chruby/chruby.sh"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"source </span><span class="si">$(</span>brew <span class="nt">--prefix</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">/opt/chruby/share/chruby/auto.sh"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc</code></pre></figure> <p>Finally, we could add a further line to switch to our newly installed version:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"chruby ruby-3.1.3"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc </code></pre></figure> <p>And that’s it! Now we have Ruby installed and ready to use on our system.</p> <h2 id="1-get-your-template">1 Get your template</h2> <p>To start, we need to choose a Jekyll theme that will serve as a foundation for our website. Fortunately, there are many free options available online, which can be easily accessed through platforms like <a href="https://github.com/search?q=jekyll+theme">GitHub</a>. For this tutorial, we will be using the <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> theme, which is a simple and elegant option for academics.</p> <p>Once you have chosen your preferred theme, the next step is to fork the repository. To do this, simply click on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Use this template</code> button and select <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Create a new repository</code> from the dropdown menu. This will create a new repository on your GitHub profile that contains all the files from the original theme repository.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/create_new_repo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="create new repo" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Make sure to rename the repository to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YOURUSERNAME.github.io</code> so that it can be properly published as a GitHub Pages site.</p> <h2 id="2-clone-your-repository">2 Clone your repository</h2> <p>Now that we have our repository set up on GitHub, we’ll want to clone it to our local machine so we can start customizing it.</p> <p>First, click on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Code</code> button on the repository page and copy the URL provided.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/clone_repo_edit.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="clone a repo" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Next, open up your terminal and navigate to the directory where you want to store your project. Once you’re in the right directory, run the command:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">git clone YOUR_REPOSITORY_URL</code></pre></figure> <p>where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YOUR_REPOSITORY_URL</code> is the URL you copied earlier. This will download all of the code from your GitHub repository onto your local machine, allowing you to make changes to the site configuration and content.</p> <h2 id="3-modify-the-code">3 Modify the code</h2> <p>Now that we have the code on our local machine, we can start modifying it. Here are some files you might want to check if you decided to use my same theme:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code>: this is a configuration file schema, and contains several information that will be used for the creation of the website</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_news</code>: folder containing news announcements as markdown files</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/about.md</code>: markdown file that should contain your personal information</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/cv.md</code>: markdown file used to provide CV information together with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_data/cv.yml</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/dropdown.md</code>: markdown file for defining submenus</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/projects.md</code>: markdown file used to render information on projects you are working on. It takes the information from the markdown files contained in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_projects</code> folder</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/publications.md</code>: markdown file used to render the publications provided in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_bibliography/papers.bib</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/repositories.md</code>: markdown file used to render information on the repositories provided in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_data/repositories.yml</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/teaching.md</code>: markdown file that should contain your teaching experience</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code>: folder containing blog entries as markdown files</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_sass</code>: folder containing Sassy Cascading Style Sheets for the website</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">assets/img</code>: folder containing images</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">assets/pdf</code>: folder containing pdf files</li> </ul> <p>Since sometimes there are execution issues, you might also want to add this lines to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.github/workflows/deploy.yml</code>:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-yml" data-lang="yml"><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="na">jobs</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="na">deploy</span><span class="pi">:</span>
        <span class="na">runs-on</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">ubuntu-latest</span>
        <span class="na">steps</span><span class="pi">:</span>
        <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Fix permission</span>
            <span class="s">run</span><span class="err">:</span> <span class="pi">|</span>
                <span class="s">chmod a+x bin/*</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></figure> <h2 id="4-build-it-locally">4 Build it locally</h2> <p>We can now build our website and make it available on a local server by running the following command:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">bundle <span class="nb">exec </span>jekyll serve</code></pre></figure> <p>This allows us to check if everything is as we expected, or if we need further refinement. After running the command, we can go to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">http://localhost:4000/</code> on our web browser to see the website locally.</p> <h2 id="5-stage-and-commit-the-changes">5 Stage and commit the changes</h2> <p>Once you have made changes to your website and are happy with them, you need to commit them. Commits are like snapshots of your repository at specific times and are the building blocks of “save points” within Git’s version control. It’s always good to check in which branch you are on before committing, since the changes are created on your current branch. We can do this by running the command:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">git status</code></pre></figure> <p>In my case, the output confirms that I’m on the master branch. If you’re on the correct branch, proceed to the next step.</p> <p>Before committing our changes, we need to add the files to the staging area. In fact, Git only looks to the staging area to determine what to commit. To stage files, run the command:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">git add &lt;FILENAME&gt;</code></pre></figure> <p>Once done, we can commit the files including a commit message by running the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git commit</code> with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-m</code> option:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">git commit <span class="nt">-m</span> <span class="s2">"descriptive commit message"</span></code></pre></figure> <p>Remember that without staging any files the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git commit</code> won’t work.</p> <p>You can speed up the process using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-a</code> option that allows to stage all the files that are already being tracked by Git and commits them:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">git commit <span class="nt">-am</span> <span class="s2">"descriptive commit message"</span></code></pre></figure> <h2 id="6-push-your-commits">6 Push your commits</h2> <p>After committing your changes locally, you need to share them with the remote repository. This step is necessary to update the corresponding branch on the remote server. To upload all local branch commits to the remote, use the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git push</code>:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">git push</code></pre></figure> <p>Once you have published your local changes to the remote repository, you are ready to build your website.</p> <h2 id="7-deploy-the-website">7 Deploy the website</h2> <p>Finally, we can deploy our website on GitHub. For doing so, the preferred way is by executing the following command:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">bin/deploy <span class="nt">--user</span></code></pre></figure> <p>If the GitHub Actions are properly setup, your personal website should be built and available in few minutes!</p> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <p>This blog post was created using the following resources:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</a></li> <li><a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/macos/">Jekyll and Ruby’s installation guide</a></li> <li><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/">Markdown</a></li> <li><a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/git-guides">Git Guide</a></li> <li><a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/issues/6">Why you should use bin/deploy</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.moncefbelyamani.com/why-you-shouldn-t-use-the-system-ruby-to-install-gems-on-a-mac/">Why you shouldn’t use the macOS system Ruby</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="github"/><category term="jekyll"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a quick tutorial on setting up your personal website on github.]]></summary></entry></feed>